const questionBank = [
  {
    "question": "The total market value of all the final goods and services produced in an economy over a given period of time is known as",
    "options": [
      "aggregate supply.",
      "Gross Domestic Product (GDP).",
      "Gross National Product (GNP).",
      "the national debt."
    ],
    "answer": 2,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is most likely to cause a shift to the left in the demand curve for a good?",
    "options": [
      "A fall in the price of the good",
      "A fall in the price of a complement",
      "A fall in the price of a substitute",
      "An increase in consumers’ income"
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Figure 1 shows the supply and demand curves in the market for a product. The initial equilibrium is at $P_{1}$ $Q_{1}$ . The government then introduces a tax on the product. Following the introduction of the tax, the new equilibrium is at $P_{2}$ $Q_{2}$ .",
    "options": [
      "The total revenue of the firms in the industry increases by $P_{2}$ minus $P_{1}$ multiplied by $Q_{2}$.",
      "The total amount paid by consumers for the product increases by the area $P_{1}$ $P_{2}$ $BC$.",
      "The total revenue of the firms in the industry falls by the area $P_{2}$ $P_{1}$ $CB$.",
      "The total amount spent by consumers on the product increases by the area $P_{2}$ $P_{1}$ $BC$."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Hard"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is most likely to reduce the price elasticity of supply of a firm’s products?",
    "options": [
      "An increase in the number of firms in the industry",
      "An increase in the firm’s spare production capacity",
      "A reduction in the time it takes to produce the product",
      "A reduction in the availability of the raw materials used to produce the product"
    ],
    "answer": 4,
    "difficulty": "Hard"
  },
  {
    "question": "A free good is a product which",
    "options": [
      "has a perfectly inelastic supply.",
      "has zero marginal utility.",
      "is not scarce.",
      "is not subject to the law of diminishing returns."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is a macroeconomic objective?",
    "options": [
      "Allocative efficiency",
      "Productive efficiency",
      "Redistribution of income and wealth",
      "Static efficiency"
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is most likely to be a characteristic of a public good?",
    "options": [
      "Non-excludability",
      "Private ownership",
      "Rivalry in consumption",
      "Zero marginal cost"
    ],
    "answer": 1,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A firm has total costs of £200 when its output is 10 units and total costs of £210 when its output is 11 units. The marginal cost of the 11th unit is",
    "options": [
      "£10",
      "£20",
      "£21",
      "£210"
    ],
    "answer": 1,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gini coefficient is correct? The Gini coefficient",
    "options": [
      "can be used to compare income inequality between countries.",
      "is measured on the horizontal axis of the Lorenz curve diagram.",
      "is a measure of the extent of relative poverty in an economy.",
      "is equal to zero in an economy where there is perfect inequality."
    ],
    "answer": 1,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "An example of a supply-side policy is",
    "options": [
      "a reduction in the rate of interest.",
      "an increase in the rate of income tax.",
      "an increase in government spending on infrastructure.",
      "the central bank selling government bonds."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is a consequence of the basic economic problem of limited resources and unlimited wants?",
    "options": [
      "All goods and services will have a market price",
      "Employment of factors of production has an opportunity cost",
      "Markets are unable to allocate resources efficiently",
      "There will not be an excess supply in markets"
    ],
    "answer": 2,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A profit-maximising firm, in the service sector, needs to recruit a new employee. Which one of the following explains why asymmetric information could mean that the most suitable person is not chosen?",
    "options": [
      "It is difficult to calculate the marginal revenue productivity of workers in the service sector",
      "Occupational immobility of labour means that there is a limited supply of workers with the right skill set",
      "The firm may have to recruit the worker from the local area because labour is often geographically immobile",
      "The firm is unlikely to know everything about job applicant's skills, abilities and motivation"
    ],
    "answer": 4,
    "difficulty": "Hard"
  },
  {
    "question": "If production has moved from Point A to Point B, which one of the following must be true?",
    "options": [
      "Allocative efficiency in the car industry is unchanged",
      "Demand for electric-powered vehicles has increased",
      "Productive efficiency in the car industry is unchanged",
      "Static efficiency in the car industry has improved"
    ],
    "answer": 4,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "A household's annual income increases from £35 000 to £38 500. All other things being equal, if the household's income elasticity of demand for Good X is -0.2 and its income elasticity of demand for Good Y is 0.4, which one of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Spending on Good X will fall by £70 and spending on Good Y will increase by £140",
      "Spending on Good X will fall by £700 and spending on Good Y will increase by £1400",
      "Spending on Good X will fall by 2% and spending on Good Y will increase by 4%",
      "Spending on Good X will fall by 20% and spending on Good Y will increase by 40%"
    ],
    "answer": 1,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fall in price and increase in the quantity demanded of lemons could have been caused by",
    "options": [
      "a fall in the price of a substitute for lemons, oranges.",
      "a rise in the price of lemonade.",
      "a reduction in the price of a complement for lemons, fish.",
      "favourable weather leading to a record harvest."
    ],
    "answer": 4,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The environment is a scarce resource. A consequence of this is that",
    "options": [
      "all natural resources have a market price.",
      "all natural resources will eventually be used up.",
      "the environment has an opportunity cost.",
      "the environment is a pure public good."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "A positive statement",
    "options": [
      "does not take into account irrational behaviour.",
      "enables accurate forecasts to be made.",
      "includes a value judgement.",
      "may be true or false."
    ],
    "answer": 4,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is a nudge technique that could be used to encourage healthy eating?",
    "options": [
      "Banning supermarkets from selling high-calorie energy drinks",
      "Increasing taxes on high-fat products to raise their price",
      "Moving products with a high sugar content away from supermarket checkouts",
      "Subsidising fruit and vegetables to reduce their prices"
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average university graduate can expect to earn more over their working life than the average school leaver. This is most likely to be explained by",
    "options": [
      "discrimination in the labour markets for non-graduates.",
      "the higher marginal revenue productivity of graduates.",
      "the higher price elasticity of demand for graduates.",
      "the relatively low elasticity of supply of non-graduates."
    ],
    "answer": 2,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements regarding supply-side policies is correct? Supply-side policies",
    "options": [
      "can have microeconomic as well as macroeconomic effects on the economy.",
      "can increase the potential output of an economy but not its trend rate of growth.",
      "cannot be used to correct market failures and improve the operation of markets.",
      "do not affect competitiveness or the current account of the balance of payments."
    ],
    "answer": 1,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Economics is a social science because",
    "options": [
      "all economic hypotheses are based on value judgements.",
      "economic policies can only be based on positive analysis.",
      "it involves the study of human behaviour and economic decision making",
      "quantitative data cannot be used to test economic theories."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Easy"
  },
  {
    "question": "All other things being equal, the demand for labour is more likely to be wage elastic if",
    "options": [
      "it is difficult to substitute capital for labour.",
      "the cost of labour is a low percentage of total costs.",
      "the final product has a high price elasticity of demand.",
      "the supply curve for labour is wage elastic."
    ],
    "answer": 3,
    "difficulty": "Medium"
  }
]

module.exports = questionBank;